Guide to the Nicholas School of the Environment Records, 1916-ongoing UA.18.01.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Nicholas School of the Environment records
1916-ongoing
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Nicholas School of the Environment (Duke University)
UA.18.01.0001
41.25 Linear Feet
32.2 Gigabytes
Duke University's Nicholas School of the Environment traces its beginnings to the founding of the Duke School of Forestry in 1938. In the 1990s two other entities, the Duke Marine Laboratory and the Duke Department of Geology, were combined with Forestry to form the Nicholas School. The Records of Duke University's Nicholas School of the Environment, 1916-ongoing, contain materials created from the school's inception as the Duke School of Forestry (1938) through all its subsequent names: the School of Forestry and Environmental Studies, the School of the Environment, and the Nicholas School of the Environment and Earth Sciences. The collection also includes material about the history of Duke Forest and its use as a teaching and research facility. The earliest materials comprise the papers of Clarence F. Korstian, first director of the Forest and first dean of the School, including his correspondence, early reports about the Forest and the School, and his involvement in the Ecological Society of America, the North Carolina Forestry Association, and the International Union of Forest Research Organizations. The bulk of the collection consists of the School's general administrative records, including annual reports, admissions records, enrollment statistics, information on degrees granted, faculty history and meetings, and surveys and meetings of the School's alumni. Visual materials include posters, color and black-and-white photographs, negatives, slides, and digital photographs that document the School of Forestry and the Duke Marine Laboratory.
Access Restrictions
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Provenance
The Nicholas School of the Environment Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer, 1974-2019.
Biographical and Historical Note
Forestry studies at Duke University can be traced to 1931, when several of the nearby small farms and forestlands the university had been purchasing since the mid-1920s were formally named as Duke Forest. When the School of Forestry was established in 1938, it was the first graduate school in its field in the South. A chronology of its history follows below.
Chronology
1930 Clarence F. Korstian appointed as first Director of Duke Forest
1931 Duke Forest formally named
1932 First classes in forestry taught at Duke University
1938 School of Forestry founded, with Korstian appointed as Dean
1970s Curriculum expanded to include broader range of ecological sciences
1974 Renamed School of Forestry and Environmental Studies
1991 Merged with the Duke Marine Laboratory (founded 1938) and renamed School of the Environment
1995 Renamed Nicholas School of the Environment following upon gift of Peter and Virginia Nicholas
1997 Division of Earth and Ocean Sciences created when the former Department of Geology (founded 1936) joins school
2000 School re-named Nicholas School of the Environment and Earth Sciences
2008-2009 Name reverted to Nicholas School of the Environment
Collection Overview
The Records of Duke University's Nicholas School of the Environment contain materials created during the school's entire history, from its founding as the Duke School of Forestry, in 1938, through all its subsequent names: the School of Forestry and Environmental Studies, the School of the Environment, and the Nicholas School of the Environment and Earth Sciences. The collection also includes materials about the closely-related Duke Forest, especially its history and the School's management and use of it as a teaching and research facility. The earliest materials here comprise the papers of Clarence F. Korstian, first director of the Forest and first dean of the School; his files include his personal correspondence, early reports about the Forest and the School, and material about several professional organizations, particularly the Ecological Society of America, the North Carolina Forestry Association, and the International Union of Forest Research Organizations. Following Korstian's papers, the bulk of the collection consists of the School's general administrative records, including all the following: annual reports, admissions records, enrollment statistics, and information on degrees granted; faculty history, curricula, and meetings; and extensive data on the School's alumni, especially alumni surveys and newsletters and meetings of the Alumni Association. The administrative records are supplemented by extensive visual materials; these contain a small selection of posters and other promotional materials about the School, but primarily consist of approximately 5000 color and black-and-white photographs, negatives, slides, and digital photographs that document a wide variety of faculty and student history and activities at both the School of Forestry and the Duke Marine Laboratory. Arranged in order by accession number, with several small, related accessions merged into single series.
Conditions Governing Access
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
Conditions Governing Access
Portions of these materials are restricted by donor request.
Conditions Governing Access
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use of administrative records. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Conditions Governing Access
Access copies of electronic records must be requested through the collection guide and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
Forests and forestry -- Research -- North Carolina; Duke Forest (N.C.) -- History; Forestry schools and education -- North Carolina -- Durham; Forests and forestry -- North Carolina; Black-and-white photographs; Color photographs; Duke Forest (N.C.) -- Research; Duke Forest (N.C.) -- Study and teaching; Posters; Negatives (photographs); Slides (photographs); Forest management; Forest management -- North Carolina -- Durham; Environmental sciences -- North Carolina; Environmental sciences -- Study and teaching; Nicholas School of the Environment and Earth Sciences (Duke University) -- History; Nicholas School of the Environment and Earth Sciences (Duke University); North Carolina Forestry Association; Duke University. School of Forestry; Duke University. School of the Environment; Duke University. School of Forestry and Environmental Studies -- Alumni and alumnae; Duke University. School of Forestry and Environmental Studies; Korstian, Clarence F. (Clarence Ferdinand), 1889-1968; Nicholas School of the Environment (Duke University) -- History; Ecological Society of America; International Union of Forest Research Organizations; Duke University -- Degrees; Duke University -- Students; Duke University. Marine Laboratory; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University -- History -- 20th century
- UA 74-115 and UA 85-51: Clarence F. Korstian Records, 1916-1960, 3 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  These two accessions comprise the records of Clarence F. Korstian, first director of Duke Forest and first dean of the School of Forestry, and cover some forty-five years of his career, both prior to and following his Duke appointment in 1930. Duke materials document his years at the School of Forestry and include early reports to the President, studies such as the Loblolly Pine Project, and his involvement in several professional organizations, including the Ecological Society of America, the International Union of Forest Research Organizations, and the North Carolina Forestry Association. Arranged in alphabetical order by topic except for the first folder, a 1959 interview of Korstian about his long career.
  - Clarence F. Korstian: Forty Years of Forestry, oral history interview, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Budget--library, 1935-1943, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Building--School of Forestry, 1938-1950 (Box 1)
  - Clippings--Durham, 1930-1931 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, miscellaneous--alphabetical file (partial), 1920-1946, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence on forestry legislation, 1944-1945 (Box 1)
  - Duke Forest Fund, 1931-1957, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Duke School of Forestry--Development Plan, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Duke School of Forestry--Reports to the President Report, 1937-1948 (Box 1)
  - Duke University--correspondence and printed material, 1923-1949, 3 folders (Box 1)
    Much of this correspondence relates to Korstian's appointment as Director of the Duke Forest and Professor of Silviculture, 1930. Includes President W. P. Few's A.L.S. to Korstian, 1930 July 4.
  - Ecological Society of America--correspondence, 1916-1945, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Ecological Society of America (ESA). Committee on the Preservation of Natural Conditions, 1918-1946, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Education, 1930-1936, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Educational Plans and Policy, 1927-1938 (Box 2)
  - Ethics, Professional, 1947-1954 (Box 2)
  - International Union of Forest Research Organizations--correspondence, 1931-1941, 1952-1958, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - International Union of Forest Research Organizations--foreign circulars, 1936-1938, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - International Union of Forest Research Organizations--minutes, 1954-1958, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - International Union of Forest Research Organizations--miscellaneous material, 1935-1954, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Keep North Carolina Green, 1933-1947 (Box 2)
  - Loblolly Pine Project--correspondence with Southeastern Forest Experiment Station, 1953-1960 (Box 2)
  - Loblolly Pine Project--declined, 1954-1956, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Loblolly Pine Project--Wahlenberg, 1954-1960, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Misc. articles and speeches, 1916-1936 (Box 3)
  - North Carolina Forestry Association, 1940-1953, 14 folders (Box 3)
  - North Carolina Forestry Association--constitution and by-laws, 1943-1946 (Box 3)
  - North Carolina Forestry Association. Cutting Practice Control Committee, 1944-1946 (Box 3)
  - North Carolina Forestry Association. Forestry Policy Committee, 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - North Carolina Forestry Association. Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1939-1951 (Box 3)
  - North Carolina Forestry Association--speakers, service, 1944-1950 (Box 3)
  - North Carolina--State Forestry Survey, 1945-1952 (Box 3)
  - Personal, 1923-1933 (Box 3)
  - School of Forestry--scholarships and fellowships, 1935-1944 (Box 3)
  - Sigma Xi, 1931-1935 (Box 3)
  - Staff Meetings, 1944-1949 (Box 4)
  - Veterans Administration, 1946-1949, 2 folders (Box 4)
- UA 86-17, 1939-1984, 1 box
  Reports, clippings, press releases, information on creative retrenchment, and a folder concerning the career of William Maughn and the establishment of the Maughan Memorial Lecture series. Arranged in alphabetical order by topic.
  - Continuation Proposal, Eastern Deciduous Forest Biome, International Biological Program, 1972-1974 (Box 4)
  - Creative Retrenchment news clippings, 1979 (Box 4)
  - "Directions for Progress" (excerpts), 1980 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous news clippings, 1976-1979 (Box 4)
  - "Planning for the Eighties" (excerpts), 1978 (Box 4)
  - "Position Papers: Student Representatives to the Ad Hoc Committee," 1980 (Box 4)
  - Press releases, 1978-1979, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Retrenchment memos and report information, 1975-1984 (Box 4)
  - William Maughan Memorial Lecture, 1939-1976 (Box 4)
- UA 86-44, 1977-1980, 1 box
  Correspondence about and texts of the first few lectures in the Maughn Memorial Lectures series, in chronological order.
  - Maughan Memorial Lectures, 1977-1980, 6 folders (Box 4)
- UA 88-47, 1935-1985, 3 boxes
  Records concerning admissions, commencements, committees, curricula, enrollment statistics, summer programs and sessions, and other administrative activities, predominantly from the 1970s and early 1980s. Arranged alphabetically by topic, except for the extensive Red Cedar Study, circa 1935, which is housed at the end of the accession.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  [FERPA RESTRICTIONS NOTE: Certain folders, as stamped, are restricted under FERPA.]
  - Admissions, 1960-1984
    [FERPA RESTRICTIONS NOTE: The 2nd "admissions" folder below is restricted under FERPA.]
    - GRE scores and GPA grad student admissions data, 1960-1984 (Box 4)
    - GRE scores and GPA of professional and graduate students, 1960-1984 (Box 4)
    - Student recruitment, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - Alumni questionnaire--master's project role in professional degree programs, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Brochures--employment profile, SFES flyer, SFES graduates, 1984 (Box 4)
  - Coastal Zone Program, 1979-1980 (Box 4)
  - Commencement, 1976-1983, 8 folders (Box 4)
  - Committees (Awards; Courses and Curriculum; and Faculty Council), 1971-1982, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Computer Facilities, 1976-1979 (Box 4)
  - Course Census, 1969-1979 (Box 4)
  - Course descriptions (FES 322--Microbiology of Forest Soils, 1973-1975 (Box 4)
  - Degrees--Doctor of Forestry, 1947-1971 (Box 5)
  - Degrees--Doctor of Philosophy, 1938 to Present,1983 (Box 5)
  - Duke Forest Annual Report, 1981-1983 (Box 5)
  - Duke Forest surveys--data tables and map, undated, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Employment status for 1971-1977 graduates, circa 1978 (Box 5)
  - Enrollment, 1979-1980 (Box 5)
  - Enrollment figures, 1979-1980 (Box 5)
  - Enrollment forecasts, 1970-1982 (Box 5)
  - Enrollment lists, 1938-1979, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Faculty handbook, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Faculty, list of, 1930-1983 (Box 5)
  - Faculty meetings, 1980-1982 (Box 5)
  - Faculty photographs, circa 1939 (Box 5)
  - Financial Awards, 1966-1982 (Box 5)
    FERPA RESTRICTED.
  - Graduate enrollment, 1965-1985 (Doctoral degree placements, faculty and dissertations supervised), 1985 (Box 5)
  - Graduate School of Natural Resources, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Graduate students entering, 1975-1981 (Box 5)
  - Instructor evaluation (course evaluation), 1985-1987 (Box 5)
  - Instructor evaluation (Royer and Smart), 1979-1985 (Box 5)
  - Loose materials (filing system outline?), 1986 (Box 5)
  - Maughan Lecture Series, 1979-1981 (Box 5)
  - Planning and Development Goals of the Dean of SFES, 1977-1978 (Box 5)
  - Planning and Development--program development and definition, 1976-1978 (Box 5)
  - Policy and procedures manual, 1975-1977 (Box 5)
  - Course offerings, Fall 1979 (Box 5)
  - "Report on SFES," Benjamin A. Jayne, Dean, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Summer course--FES 291, 1979, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Summer Program, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Summer Program and faculty suggestions, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Summer Program, proposed, undated (Box 5)
  - Summer session, 1971-1980, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Summer session equipment information, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Summer session planning, 1977-1978 (Box 5)
  - Timberland Marketplace for Buyers, Sellers and Investors and their Advisors, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Vehicle Reports, 1975-1985 (Box 5)
  - Red Cedar Study, 1935-1938 (Box 6)
    - Board feet, undated (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1935-1938 (Box 6)
    - Durham Division, Map 7, 1935-1938 (Box 6)
    - Field Data--Stands, 5, 6, 7, 11, 18 (trees 1-100), 1935, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - Logarithmic tables, 1935-1937 (Box 6)
    - Methods, undated (Box 6)
- UA 89-21, UA 89-54, UA 90-66, UA 92-84, and UA 94-139, 1957-1994
  The largest of these accessions, UA 89-54, and the four smaller ones primarily comprise FES Alumni Association activities and records and have been interfiled together, with original accession number noted on individual folders. Materials include alumni surveys, correspondence, minutes of the Alumni Association's Executive Council meetings, reunions, and routine mailings to members. A small group of general files, unrelated to the Alumni Association, is gathered at the end of these accessions: these include various annual reports and some files about the proposed phaseout of the School of Forestry in the mid-1970s. Arranged in alphabetical order by topic.
  - Alumni Association (AA) files, 1957-1994, 60 folders (Box 6)
    - A.T. Davison Records, 1958-1960 (Box 6)
    - Alumni surveys, 1970-1980 (Box 6)
    - Annual meeting, 1981 (Box 6)
    - Bylaws, 1993 (Box 6)
    - Bylaws and officers 1980-1988 (Box 6)
    - Class newsletters, 1987-1990, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Correspondence--general/miscellaneous, 1957-1965, 1980-1989, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Correspondence--Executive Council, 1981-1990, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - Correspondence--receptions and reunions, 1979-1982 (Box 6)
    - Dues collection mailings, 1983-1990, 6 folders (Box 6)
    - "Employment Status of 1938-80 Graduates," 1981-1982 (Box 6)
    - Executive Council meetings, 1983-1989, 13 folders (Box 6)
    - Executive Council meetings, 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Executive Council minutes (cumulative), 1981-1994 (Box 7)
    - Fellowships, 1985-1989, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Field Day Reunion, general information and invitations, 1984 (Box 7)
    - Financial statements, 1981-1985, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Information packets (to grads), 1987-1989, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Meetings--local, 1983-1985 (Box 7)
    - Meetings--Tacoma and Portland, 1983 (Box 7)
    - Membership lists, 1982-1988, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Policy manual, 1982 (Box 7)
    - Reunions (Classes of '61, '62, '63, '77, and '78), 1986-1988, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - General Files, 1975-1988, 19 folders
    - Annual Reports of the Duke Forest, Fiscal Years 1976/77 through 1982/83, 1976-1983, 7 folders (Box 7)
    - Annual Report, SFES, FY 1976/77, 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Annual Report, SFES, FY 1979/80, 1979-1980 (Box 7)
    - Board of Visitors meetings, 1980-1985 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence--Reed Kelly to Harmon L. Smith, 1980 (Box 7)
    - "Directions for Progress: A Report to the Duke University Board of Trustees," 1980 (Box 7)
    - Phaseout--correspondence, reports, and newspaper coverage, 1975, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - "Planning for the Eighties: A Report to the Duke University Board of Trustees"; and "Planning for the Eighties, a Response," 1978-1979 (Box 7)
    - Sociey of American Foresters--annual conventions, 1976-1980 (Box 7)
    - Student recruitment posters, 1977-1988 (Box 7)
- UA 91-126 and UA 94-74, 1978-1992
  These two accessions primarily consist of memoranda, news releases, clippings, and other public relations material sent to the Campus Calendar, Duke Dialogue, Faculty Newsletter, and other media. Also includes correspondence and material about conference, workshops, and other events sponsored by the School. The smaller accession, 94-74 (8 folders) has been interfiled with the larger, though noted on individual folders. Arranged in order by the office's filing system codes in use at the time, as follows: DU (Duke University); FES (Forestry and Environmental Studies); MSC (Meetings, Symposia, Conferences); and PR (unidentified, but presumably Public Relations).
  - DU: Calendar, 1978-1983, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - DU: Faculty Newsletter, 1978-1984, 6 folders (Box 7)
  - FES: Center for Forestry Investment, 1983-1985 (Box 8)
  - FES: Hazardous wastes public survey--Executive Summary clippings, 1981 (Box 8)
  - FES: Seminar announcements, 1981-1983, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - MSC: "Accounting for the Money" conference, 1981 (Box 8)
  - MSC: Forestry accounting and control seminar, 1982 (Box 8)
  - MSC: Legal problems of woodland operations, 1980-1981 (Box 8)
  - MSC: NIPF--a Review of Economic and Policy Studies, 1983 (Box 8)
  - MSC: Nonindustrial private forests--data needs, 1980-1981 (Box 8)
  - MSC: Pocosins conference and Pocosins map (North Carolina), 1979-1982, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - MSC: Reorganization conference, 1979, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - MSC: Timber and timberland asset values conference, 1983 (Box 8)
  - MSC: "Timber and Timberland Valuation in the Eyes of the Court," 1981 (Box 8)
  - MSC: Timberland Marketplace proceedings, 1991 (Box 8)
  - MSC: U.S. dependency on Canadian natural resources, 1979-1980 (Box 8)
  - MSC: "Woodburning car" seminar, 1981 (Box 8)
  - MSC: Workshop on Financing Forestry Investments, 1982 (Box 8)
  - PR: Duke Calendar, 1984-1985 (Box 8)
  - PR: Duke Dialogue, 1986-1992, 6 folders (Box 8)
  - PR: Duke Faculty Newsletter, 1984-1986, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - PR: Fellowship awards and recipients, 1980-1983, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - PR: Honor roll / fellowships, 1986 (Box 8)
  - PR: Industry fellowships and scholarships, 1983-1985, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - PR: Mellon Grant--systems science, news releases, 1981 (Box 8)
  - PR: News clippings, 1980-1985, 5 folders (Box 8)
  - PR: News and press releases, 1980-1992, 8 folders (Box 8)
  - PR: Seminar announcements, 1984-1985 (Box 8)
  - PR: Summer field program, 1982 (Box 8)
- UA 93-95, 1984-1989
  Two alumni surveys, interfiled together, conducted in 1984 (unstamped) and 1989 (date-stamped). Questions posed to alumni include positions held since graduation, current activities, effectiveness of the school for training, and involvement in alumni affairs. Arranged in alphabetical order by respondents' surnames.
  - Alumni Survey, A-K, 1984-1989, 14 folders (Box 8)
  - Alumni Survey, L-Z, 1984-1989, 16 folders (Box 9)
- UA 93-106, 1979-1988, 2 boxes
  Proceedings and other materials from various conferences and workshops sponsored by the School; in many cases, multiple instances of the workshops are represented, spanning several years. Arranged as received.
  - Reorganization: Issues, Implications, 1979 (Box 9)
  - Acid Deposition Meeting, 1985 (Box 9)
  - Accounting Seminar, 1981-1983, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - American Land Resources Association, 1985 (Box 9)
  - Assessing Data Needs Concerning Private Non-Industrial Forestlands, 1980 (Box 9)
  - Canadian Consulate Equipment Demo, 1983 (Box 9)
  - Competition for Land in the American South, 1985 (Box 9)
  - Conference on the Future of N.C. National Forests, 1984 (Box 9)
  - Consulting Foresters Meeting, 1984 (Box 9)
  - Coordinating Timberland Appraisal, 1987 (Box 9)
  - Dynamuse, 1982-1984, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Dynast Update, Dr. Boyce, 1983 (Box 9)
  - EPA Wetland, 1985 (Box 9)
  - Evaluating Returns to Southern Forestry Research, 1982 (Box 9)
  - Forest Policies Meeting, 1982 (Box 9)
  - Forestry Legal Seminar, 1980-1981, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Forestry Investment Workshop, 1982 (Box 9)
  - Growing Taxes and Growing Trees, 1987 (Box 9)
  - Non-Industrial Private Forests Seminar, 1983 (Box 9)
  - Systems Dynamics Workshop, 1983 (Box 9)
  - Remote Sensing, 1985 (Box 9)
  - Participatory Management, 1985 (Box 9)
  - Travelers Timberland Investment Seminar, 1985 (Box 9)
  - Parks-Land Area Research, 1988 (Box 9)
  - 50th Anniversary, 1988 (Box 9)
  - Timberland Marketplace, 1984-1985, 13 folders (Box 10)
    Syllabi and other course materials from several instances of this workshop offered at Duke and in New Orleans and Portland in 1984-1985.
- UA 93-107, 1940-1993
  Correspondence, reports, printed material, photographs and negatives, and other materials concerning public relations, alumni affairs, and reaccreditation. Also includes alumni newsletters, the report of self-evaluation of the School of Forestry done for the Society of American Foresters, brochures, and annual reports. Arranged in alphabetical order by topic.
  - AA (Alumni Association), 1940-1993, 11 folders (Box 10)
    - By-Laws, 1953 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence, 1941-1959, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Alumni News Letter, vols. 1, 2, 4, 5, 1940-1945 (Box 10)